A Guide to the Newport News/Warwick County (Va.) Records, circa 1860-1941
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Newport News/Warwick County (Va.) Records, circa 1860-1941
The Library of Virginia
1007547, 1012852, 1012883, 1012885-1012888, 1012890, 1012899, 1012906, 1012917, 1012919, 1125003, 1202662
14 boxes
Newport News (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court records from Newport News.
Historical Information
Warwick County (extinct) was named for Robert Rich, earl of Warwick, a prominent member of the London Company, or for the county of Warwick in England. The county was originally called Warwick River and was one of the original shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634. The name was shortened to Warwick in 1643. Warwick County became extinct in 1952, when it became the city of Warwick. The new city was consolidated with the city of Newport News in 1958 and took the latter's name.
Newport News probably commemorated Christopher Newport, who made five voyages to Virginia between 1607 and 1619. The Old Dominion Land Company bought land there in 1880 and began laying out a new village in October. Newport News was incorporated as a city by Act of the General Assembly in 1896 without ever having been incorporated as a town. On 1 July 1958 Newport News was enlarged by oonsolidating with the City of Warwick, which then became extinct. In the years before consolidation, Newport News annexed land from Warwick County in 1917, 1921 and 1940; from Elizabeth City County in 1927 and 1937; and from both Elizabeth City County and Warwick counties in 1921.
Warwick County court records were destroyed several times, with most destruction occuring during the Civil War. The clerk's office was burned on 15 December 1864. County court minute books and loose records from 1787 to 1819 were destroyed by this fire. Additiona records were burned on 3 April 1865, in Richmond, where the county records had been moved for safekeeping during the Civil War.
Scope and Content
Newport News/Warwick County (Va.) Records, circa 1860-1941, consist of the following series: County and City Court Records (subfield series include Judgments, Clerk' Records, Jury Records and Chancery Records (post 1912), Election Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, County Administrative Records (subfield series include Board of Supervisors Records and Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records), Tax and Fiscal Records, Business Records, Organization Records, Fiduciary Records, Wills, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records and Land Records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Newport News and Warwick County Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm" found on the Library of Virginia's web site.
Warwick County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Warwick County Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection.
For more information and a listing of lost records localities see Lost Records research note.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Newport News (Va.) Circuit Court.; Warwick County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia--Newport News.; Public records--Virginia--Warwick County.
Geographical Names:
Newport News (Va.)--History.; Warwick County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Newport News.; Local government records--Virginia--Warwick County.
Contents List
- Records, 1860-1910
  Court Records: Judgments from Warwick County Circuit Court, Newport News Circuit Court and Newport News Corporation Court; Election Records: Abstracts of Elections (1887-1889); Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Oaths of Office; Court Records: Judgments: Indemnifying Bonds (1887-1889), Court Records: Clerks' correspondence, 1860s-1880s. Court Records: Chancery Records and Criminal Records: Commonwealth Causes pulled.
- Records, circa 1895-1926
  County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Board of Supervisors Minutes (1895); Court Records: Newport News Corporation Court: Judgments mostly relating to pilots vs. ship masters, 1903 circa); Tax and Fiscal Records: Ardent Spirit Permits (1924-1926.)
- Records, 1904-1941
  Court Records: Judgments, Court Records: Jury Records: Juror Lists, Court Records: Chancery Records: Post-1912 Chancery Causes; Business Records; Election Records: Notices of Candidacy and Election Expense Accounts: Organization Records; Tax and Fiscal Records: Lists of Poll Taxes Paid, 1904.
- Records, 1866-1901
  Court Records: Judgments and Subpoenas; Fiduciary Records; Business Records; Tax and Fiscal Records; Wills; Election Records.
- Records, 1884-1920
  Court Records: Judgments and Post 1912 Chancery Records from Warwick County Court and Newport News Corporation Court; Tax and Fiscal Records; Election Records; County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records.
- Records, 1866-1923
  Election Records: Election Returns and Petitions for Election; Court Records: Judgments: Executions and Jury Records: Jury Lists from County and Circuit Courts; County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records; Tax and Fiscal Records: Commonwealth Claims; Bonds/Oaths/Commissions.
- Records, 1881-1922
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Officials' Bonds, 1881-1891 and Oaths of Office, 1886-1891; Court Records: Chancery Records, 1913-1922; Military and Pension Records: Confederate Pension Lists and Applications to the Confederate Pension Board, 1900-1902.
- Records, 1896-1941
  Military and Pension Records: Petitions/Conditional Pardons, Papers(1922-41), List of Military and Fire Cos.(1897-03); Election Records: Abstracts of Votes(1896-04); Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Officials' Bonds(1896); Court Records: Newport News Corporation Court Judgments.
- Records, 1876-1923
  Court Records: Affidavits re: Miscellaneous Court Matters, Clerks' Records, Newport News Corporation Court: Judgments and Chancery Records: Pre-1913 chancery pulled; Miscellaneous Records: Powers of Attorney; Election Records: Abstracts of Votes; County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records; Unprocessed.
- Records, circa 1860-1918
  Court Records: Newport News Corporation Court: Civil Cases, 1899-1918, Court Records: County Court: Judgments; Tax and Fiscal Records: Commonwealth Claims; Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, circa 1860s-1870s, 1891, 1893; Election Records, 1865-1866.
- Records, 1872-1926
  Court Records: Judgments: Executions and Condemnations, Chancery Records: Summons and Subpoenas: Pre-1913 Chancery Pulled, Jury Records: Witness Lists; County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records; Tax and Fiscal Records. Unprocessed.
- Records, 1866-1924
  Warwick County and Newport News Corporation Court Records: Chancery Causes, 1917-1924, Judgments: Summons,Subpoenas and Executions; Tax and Fiscal Records: Erroneous Assessments, Liquor License Bonds, Commonwealth Claims; Election Records.
- Records, 1867-1897
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths; Business Records; Land Records: Lis Pendens; Miscellaneous Records: Powers of Attorney; Wills.
- Records, circa 1888-1902
  Court Records: Judgements: Warrants; County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records; Election Records.